What's an urban legend?!
都市伝説って何？
That black bike!
黒バイクだよ 首なしライダーだよ！
The headless rider!
The man riding that black bike...
黒いバイクに乗ってる男にはね
...has no head.
首から上がないの
It's completely gone, yet he can still move.
きれいになくなってるのに 動いてるんだって
It doesn't sound like that difficult of a job, but be careful anyway.
そんなに難しい仕事じゃないみたいだけど
一応気をつけてね
I don't remember anything about you becoming a crusader for justice.
オレ あんたが正義の味方になったなんて聞いてなかったけどなぁ～
What the hell are you?
何なんだよ
何なんだよ～～!!
What the hell are you?!
The headless rider?! I've heard of him!
首なしライダー？
聞いたことがある！
My friend saw him riding around.
友達が走ってるの見たって！
Well, I'm not really interested in that.
さあ？ あんまり関心ないですねぇ
If that's what you mean, I took a picture.
それだったら写真に撮りました
See?
ほら！
The headless rider?
首なしライダー？
That's this guy.
こいつっす こいつ！
I've heard of that.
聞いたことあるよねぇ
I, like, mighta seen it near Sunshine.
サンシャイン近くで見たかも～
For reals?
マジ～？
I dunno, but, like, everyone was freaking out, so it had to be him.
よく分かんないけど みんな騒いでたから きっとそうなんじゃない？
Everyone has a lot to say about her.
みんな じょう舌だ
It looks like the bike was spotted again.
また出たみたいですね～ 例のバイク
But, do you really think it's true that he has no head?
That's just ill-spirited gossip.
But I've heard some stories that are pretty believable.
Whoa...
There's no way he could be headless.
Unless he weren't human...
Then it'd be believable.
Apparently, those who know the most about it aren't talking.
本当にかかわりあいになった人は
寡黙になるらしい
Sorry, but I don't know anything about it.
ごめんなさい よく分からないんで
What do you think?
あなたはどうかな？
What impressions do you have of this headless rider?
あの伝説の首なしライダーにどんな印象を抱いてる？
Do you think she's scary? Cool? Unexpectedly kind?
怖い？ 格好いい？
実はなんだかいい人そう？
Or...
いや やっぱり…
Do you not know what to think?
どう受け止めたらいいのか分からない？
I'm going to tell you what I know about the headless rider.
今日は首なしライダーについて 僕が知っていることを教えよう
It's a long story, but I'd like you to keep an open mind.
縷縷綿綿とした話になるが
希有壮大な心で聞いてほしい
First, let me introduce myself.
まずは自己紹介しよう
I'm Kishitani Shinra, twenty-four years old.
僕は岸谷新羅 ２４歳
I'm an underground physician here in this town.
この街でもぐりの医者をやっている
To put it more clearly, I'm a black market doctor.
あえて言えば 出張闇医者だ
I treat people who've been injured by illegal weapons and
perform cosmetic surgery on people who need to change their faces.
非合法な武器で傷ついた人たちの手当てとか
顔を変えなきゃならない人たちの整形手術とか
Even though I work in this field, I'm skilled and well respected.
こう見えても 腕もいいし 信頼もあるんだ
Alright, time to get to the important part.
さて いよいよ本題だ
I'm home!
ただいま～
That's right.
そう… 僕はあの首なしライダ
I...live with the headless rider, Celty Sturluson.
セルティ·ストゥルルソンと同居している
I'm home, Celty.
帰ったよ セルティ
It was a really simple job.
こっちはよくある簡単な仕事だったよ
How about you?
そっちはどうだった？
No peeking!
のぞくな
Sorry! I didn't mean it like that! I just accidentally...
ごめん ごめん
なんというか いやらしい意味じゃなく
つい うっかり…
Umm, you look pretty pissed, huh?
なんかイラついているようだね
You might need some more calcium.
カルシウムの摂取が必要かな？
Are you saying I should eat egg shells?
That might be a good idea.
ああ いいんじゃないかな？
Well, I'm just a doctor.
もっとも 僕はあれだ
I'm not a nutritionist, so I don't know stuff like how much calcium is in egg shells or how well you could absorb it from that source.
栄養学には疎いから
卵の殻にいかほどのカルシウムが含まれているのか
どれだけ吸収効率がいいのか といった類のことは分からないけどね
I don't even know where your brain is,
so who knows how much you even need calcium.
そもそも 君の脳みそがどこにあるかも分からないのに
カルシウムがどれだけ有用か ってこともあるけどさ。
Shut up!
Hey, Celty, I'll ask you again, but how does the world look to you when you have no eyeballs?
なあ セルティ
何度も聞くけど
眼球の存在しない君には
一体この世界がどんなふうに見えるのかな？
I can't explain to other people what I don't understand.
自分で理解できないものを他人に教えることはできない
She doesn't have a head, but can see, hear, and smell.
彼女には首がないけど
視界もあるし 音も聞こえるし
においも感じてる
However, she can't see 360 degrees just because she doesn't have a head.
ただ 首がないからって 全方向が見えるわけじゃないらしい
She has only a slightly broader range of visibility than humans...
普通の人間より少し視野が広い程度みたいだ
This is nothing more than one of my hypotheses,
これは僕の推理に過ぎないけど
but regarding that mysterious, shadow-like, sci-fi
substance which keeps emanating from your body...
君の体から絶えず染み出している
その影のような不思議ＳＦとんでも物質
Do you think it collects information about your surroundings for you by releasing particles into the air and analyzing them when they return?
その粒子が光の代わりに周囲に放たれ
跳ね返ったところを吸収し
周囲の情報を得ているというのは どうかな？
Of course, then you wouldn't be able to pick up information about things from far away.
当然 遠くのものに対しては情報が不鮮明になる
I don't care.
興味ない 見えて聞こえればそれでいい
I'm fine as long as I can see and hear.
You're always like this, Celty.
セルティ… 君はいつだってそうだ
I wonder just how different the worlds you and I perceive truly are...
君の感じる世界は
果たして僕が感じてる世界とどれだけ差異があるのか
That's all I want to know.
僕はただそれが気になるだけなんだよ
This isn't just a conversation about your field of vision.
これは何も視界だけの話じゃない
It's also about your value system.
価値観の問題でもある
The value system of a fairy who just materialized in this town.
人間としての価値観ではなく
この街に具現化したただ一人の妖精…
I'd like to know what a dullahan thinks is valuable about this world...
デュラハンとして見た世界の価値ってやつをさ…
What's wrong?
どうしたんだい？
If it's okay with you, let's talk it over.
よかったら話してくれよ 何があったのか
Did something happen?
Orihara said your job today was easy, but...
今日の仕事 折原君は簡単だって言ってたけど
I finished the job without any setbacks.
仕事自体は何事もなく あっさり終わったんだ
But?
で？
I'm really thankful for couriers.
ほんとに運び屋様様だね
I'm where I am thanks to you, and you're where you are thanks to me.
あんたあってのオレ オレあってのあんた
I'd rather not believe the last part of that sentence.
あとの方は認めたくないな
Don't say that...
そう言わないで
I hope I can count on you in the future as well.
これからもよろしく頼むよ
I'd like to get along with you, you know.
あんたとは仲よくやっていきたいんだからさ
From now until forever...
この先も ずっと…
Is it just me, or are you being really creepy?
不気味さを感じるのは 気のせいか？
おっと！ 間違いなく気のせいだよ
It's totally just you.
Anyway, do you know what a dullahan is?
ところでさ あんた デュラハンって知ってる？
Apparently it's a headless fairy in Ireland,
アイルランドの首がない妖精のことらしいんだけど
but there's a caricature artist in Yoemi
park who says he's seen someone like that.
最近 代々木公園に流れてきた似顔絵描きのじいさんが
昔 それを見たって言ってんだよねぇ
I heard he kept talking about how, "She had no head! She had no head," so I wonder if he's referring to a dullahan...
そのじいさんがさぁ
「首がない 首がない」って 騒いでたらしいんだ
それって要するに デュラハンってヤツの首のことかな？
Is he still there?
まだそこにいるのか？
Hmph. Who knows.
さあ？ ちょっと分かんないけど
I knew she'd be interested.
やっぱり気になるんだ
Celty Sturluson is not human.
セルティ·ストゥルルソンは人間ではない
She's a wandering spirit that's termed a "dullahan" by Celtic lore.
俗にデュラハンと呼ばれる ケルト伝承などにうたわれる 妖精の類である
Do you know of a caricature artist?
似顔絵描きを知りませんか？
Oh, he's not here anymore.
あの人ならもういないですよ
Hey, didn't that guy say he was moving on to Yokohama?
ねえ！ あの人 横浜へ行くって言ってなかった？
Huh?
A dullahan holds its own decapitated head in its hands while she rides a two-wheeled carriage pulled by a headless horse called "Koshitabawa."
デュラハンは切り落とした自分の首を脇に抱え
コシュタバワーと呼ばれる首なし馬に引かれた二輪の馬車に乗って やってくる
It visits the houses of people who are close to dying.
彼らが訪れるのは死期が迫った人間がいる家だ
If you happen to open the door for it, your life ends.
もし うっかりと扉を開けてしまったら最後…
You're doused with blood from a wash bin.
たらいいっぱいの血液を浴びせかけられる
It'd be difficult to connect her current form to that ominous and bloody legend, though.
そんな 不吉で死のにおいに満ちた伝説と
現実の彼女の姿は簡単には結び付かないね
Except for the fact she has no head.
首がないことを除いては…
Why did she come to Ikebukuro in Tokyo, Japan?
彼女がなぜ この日本 この東京 この池袋に やってきたのか
Why is she so concerned about her own head?
なぜ こんなにも自分の首にこだわっているのか
I'll tell you about that right now.
それをこれからお話しよう
It happened twenty years ago.
今から２０年前のことだ
She awoke one day in the mountains to find that her head was gone.
彼女がある山の中で不意に目を覚ますと
いつの間にか首がなくなっていた
In that instant, she also noticed that she'd lost various memories.
その瞬間に気づいたのは さまざまな記憶が欠落していたこと
Things like her personality and memories of her past.
それは自分の行動の理由であったり
ある程度さかのぼった過去の記憶であったり
However, she remembered that she was a dullahan, her
name was Celty Sturluson, and she possessed certain abilities.
けれど 自分がデュラハンであること 名前がセルティ·ストゥルルソンであること
自分の能力の使い方に関しては確実に記憶していた
And the first thing she was surprised at was...
そして彼女がまず驚いたのは…
I don't just think about things with my head.
私は頭で物を考えていたわけじゃなかったんだ…
As she said.
ということだった
She also noticed that she felt the presence of her head nearby.
それに続いて 自分の首とおぼしき気配を感じることができるのにも気がついた
Assessing the situation, she inferred one thing.
状況を考え 彼女は一つの推理をした
That her will was shared by her body and head,
and that her lost memories must lie inside her head.
自分の意思はもともと体と頭で共有していたものであり
欠落した記憶は頭の中に含まれているのではないかと
She then made a decision.
そして 彼女は決意した
She was going to get her head back and
remember the meaning of her existence.
己の存在意義を知る首を取り戻すこと
That itself became her purpose in life.
それこそが 今の自分に与えられた存在意義だ
It's possible that her head left its body of its own free will.
もしかしたら 頭が自らの意思で体のもとを離れたのかもしれないが
Even so, she wouldn't know unless she got it back.
そうだとしても 結局は手にしてみなければ分からない
He wasn't in Yokohama anymore.
横浜にはもういなかった
I tried Tama next, then Chiba.
次は多摩
その次は千葉
No matter where I went, I couldn't find him.
どこへ行っても 行き違いだった
You should've just waited until tomorrow.
また明日にでもすればよかったじゃないか
I was desperate.
必死だった
My head might be there.
自分の首がそこにあるかもしれないんだ
I wanted to get it back no matter what.
どうしても取り戻したかった 一日も早く
Even if was only a day earlier...
I don't want to live with only vague memories anymore.
このまま… 自分の記憶もあいまいなまま生きていくのは嫌だ
Following that faint presence her head exuded, she came so far...
周囲に残るわずかな気配をたどり
ここまでやってきたものの
But apparently her head had left the country.
首はどうやら海外に渡ってしまったようだ
The ship was headed for Japan.
船の行き先は日本らしい
She decided to stow away and keep following it.
密航して 後を追うと決めたはいいが
The problem was her horse.
問題はこの馬だ
Dullahans possess horse carcasses as their servants.
これは馬の死がいに憑依させた デュラハンの使い魔のような存在だ
She could've just made it disappear,
but only her head would know where it went.
いざとなれば 消し去ってしまうこともできたのだが
果たしてその後にどこへ行ってしまうのか？
Therefore, even though she knew how
to make it disappear, she couldn't do it.
その記憶はたぶん頭の中だ
そう思うと 消し方が分かっていても
なかなか踏み切ることができない
It was then...
そんなとき…
That she...
彼女は
Came across it.
それに出会ったんだ
I couldn't find him anywhere.
結局どこにも見つからなかった
But...
けど…
Hey, I know that guy.
ああ～ その似顔絵描きなら知ってるぜ
He was in Southern Ikebukuro Park just two days ago.
おとといくらいから南池袋公園に来てたんだ
I see.
そうだ 一緒に行ってやろうか？
You want me to take you to him?
It's got to be inconvenient living like that, right?
そんなんじゃ不便だろ？ なっ？
There you go.
さあ 出来たよ
うわぁ～ すっごい！
Amazing!
He drew you prettier than you really are, Arisa.
亜梨沙より美人に描けてる
Hey!
ん？ ちょっと～！
Great job as always, mister.
おじさん さすがですね！
No, no, I still can't quite draw things the way I envision them.
いやいや
まだまだ描きたいものもまともに描けない有様でね
Thank you very much.
ありがとうございました
My pleasure.
どういたしまして
Come again!
またおいで
Okay!
は～い！
I'm sorry, but it's getting dark.
すまんが もう暗いんでな
I'm done for the day.
今日はこれで終わりだ
Is it true that you've seen a dullahan?
デュラハンを見たってのは本当か？
Huh?
Yeah...yeah, it is.
ああ 本当だとも
I saw one in the mountains of Ireland when I was young.
私が若いころアイルランドの山の中で見た
I saw it with these eyes, I'm certain.
間違いなく この目でな
What do you mean by, "It lost its head?"
"It lost its head?" That's not it.
「首をなくした」？
そうじゃない
It had no head.
首がないんだ
I can't draw it right.
首がどうしても決まらない
Look.
ほれ
It was a woman, and an extremely beautiful one at that.
女だった それもひどく美しい女だった
She passed by me on a mountain road during a really foggy night.
霧の深い夜 山道ですれ違った
She was frightening yet beautiful as she drove by at an incredible speed.
ものすごい勢いで走り去っていった 恐ろしくも美しい姿だった
I just knew she wasn't of this world.
この世のものじゃない… そう直感した
After I returned to the inn and talked to someone, he told me it was, without a doubt, a dullahan.
宿に帰って話をすると
それはデュラハンに違いないと言われた
Apparently they've inhabited that place since the olden days.
古くから その地に住んでいるんだそうだ
Why don't your dullahans hold any heads?
なぜ あなたのデュラハンは首を抱えてないんだ？
I can't draw them.
描けないんだ
The more I try to draw them, the more they vary.
描けば描くほど違って見える
My memory of that day is so vivid,
yet I can't remember that woman at all.
あの日の記憶は確かなのに どうしてもあの女にたどりつくことができない
What color was her hair? Her eyes?
What about her facial expression?
その女の髪の色は？ 目の色は？
表情はどんなだった？
If I knew, I wouldn't bother making pictures of her.
それを口にできるなら 絵にしようとは思わなかっただろう
Although, a strange man came by the other day.
そういえば 最近 妙な男が訪ねてきてな
He told me that picture was perfect.
その男はこの絵はこれで完ぺきだと言うんだ
He said she didn't have to have a head.
彼女は首がなくていいんだとね
What a weird guy.
変わった男だった
Why do you care so much about it?
なんでそこまでこだわるんだ？
That experience was the height of my life.
あの経験は私の人生で最高のものだ
That one night was my whole life.
あの夜が一生だった
I want to get back the feelings and the memories I had of that moment.
取り戻したいんだ あの瞬間 あのときの記憶を
Thanks, man.
じいさん ありがとな
I get it.
なるほどね
You don't remember meeting him at all, do you?
ところで 君はそのおじいさんと会った記憶はないんだろ？
No.
ない
That dullahan may have been you, or it may not have.
そのデュラハンは君かもしれないし 君じゃないかもしれない
Or he might have misconstrued what he saw.
あるいは単なる見間違いかもしれない
It was definitely me.
あれは私だ きっとそうだ
I know it.
Alright.
そうか…
Where was I going then?
私はどこに向かって走っていたんだろう？
What was I thinking and what was my goal?
何を思い どんな目的で…
Do you really have to worry that much about it?
そんなに気にする必要があるんだろうか？
Huh?
You can appear and disappear at will and you're refreshingly unique.
君はまさしく神出鬼没で 斬新奇抜な存在だよ
However, you're still quite far away from having your wish come true.
だからといって 今のままでは
君の望みの達成は前途遼遠だ
What are you trying to say?
何が言いたい？
It's simple...
単純に言おう あきらめなよ
Just give up.
That strange man's probably right.
その変わった男の言ったこと当たってるんじゃないかな？
You might be fine without your head.
首 なくたっていいんじゃないかな？
Let's stop looking for your head and go somewhere together.
自分の首を捜すのはもうやめてさ
二人でどこかに行こうよ
Anywhere is fine.
どこでもいい
As long as you wish it, I'll use any means
I can to get you back to your hometown.
君が望むなら 僕はどんな手を使ってでも君を故郷に帰してみせる
I'll go there, too.
僕もそこへ行くよ それでずっと一緒に…。
We'll be together forever.
I don't hate you, but I'm fine with how things are now.
お前のことは嫌いじゃないが
今こうしてここで暮らしているだけで十分だ
Don't say that—
そんなこと言わないでさ…
I'm fine!
十分だ！
Then...
だったらさ せめてもうちょっと女の子らしく…
Try being more feminine—
I've had enough!
もういい！
So, I guess our values are different after all.
やっぱり 僕の価値観と彼女の価値観には違いがあるのだろうか？
Let's end this intermission and continue with the story.
閑話休題
さっきの続きを話そうか
The story of her—no, us after we boarded that ship.
船に乗ってからの彼女の…
いや 彼女と僕の話を
She was able to talk the crew into letting her on board, but she realized her appearance made her stand out.
船員に話をつけて 密航したはいいが
彼女は自分の姿がひどく目立つことに気がついた
After knowing her for a while, I can now say it wasn't much of a shock.
彼女を知る今となってはなんてことない光景だけど…
Although, I was surprised the first time I saw her.
初めて見たときは驚いたものさ
I was four years old at the time.
僕が４歳のときだった
I was returning to Japan with my father.
僕は父さんと一緒に日本へ帰る途中だった
Dad, Dad, there's a woman in the cargo bay!
To put it nicely, my father—Shingen—wasn't someone you couldn call normal.
父の森巌は お世辞にも普通とは言えない人間だ
After hearing what I said, most parents would just ignore it.
僕が見たことを聞いたら 親としては一笑に付すのが 正しい態度じゃなかろうか
However, my father was different.
しかし 父さんは違った
Maybe it was because he was a doctor, but it piqued his interest.
医者としての性なのか
がぜん 興味を持ったんだ
Ma'am, this might be presumptuous, but is it true you have no head?
ご婦人 失礼だが
あなたには首がないというが本当かな？
So my father entreated her:
父さんは言った 一度だけでいい
"As long as you let me dissect you once, I'll give you a place to stay."
あなたを解剖させてくれれば居場所を提供しよう
She assented.
彼女は承諾した
It may have been best for her,
but I'm sure she was still worried.
打算もあれば いろいろ不安もあったろう
Apparently she doesn't remember much of what happened after that.
このときのことを彼女はあまり覚えていないらしい
Human anesthesia didn't really work on her,
so I'm sure the shock of it all was quite great.
人間用の麻酔はあまり効かず
ショックが強かったのかもしれない
It seems she can feel pain, but not nearly as acutely as a human would.
痛覚はあるようだが 人間よりはかなり鈍いようだな
She doesn't have a heart.
心臓がない
All her organs are in form only and serve no real function.
どの臓器も形だけで なんの機能もしていない
She has blood vessels, but no blood courses
through them. Her flesh is the only thing that's real.
血管はあるのに血は通っていない
ただ肉があるだけだ
It's as if she's just a model.
まるで生きている人体模型だな
But, look.
ただし 見ろ
How does she die?
こいつ どうやったら死ぬんだ？
He's a horrible father, right?
ひどい父親だろう？
He let a four year-old dissect somebody.
４歳の子供に彼女の解剖をさせようっていうんだから
Yet, thanks to his teachings, I learned how to be a surgeon.
けど こんな教育のお陰で 医者の技能が身に付いたんだから
I don't even know what you could call "fortunate" about this.
何が幸いするか分からない
What's wrong?
どうした？
The first time I saw her, I was attracted to everything about her.
ひと目見たときから 彼女に魅せられていた
My feelings for her haven't changed during the twenty years I've lived with her.
その気持ちは一緒に暮らしたこの２０年間まったく変わってない
And she continues to search for her head while working as a courier.
そして 彼女は運び屋の仕事をしながら
ずっと自分の首を捜してる
I wonder what she plans to do if she ever finds her head?
首が戻ったら 彼女はどうするつもりなんだろう？
What will happen to her?
彼女はどうなってしまうんだろう？
Is her will the same as her head's?
彼女の意思はそのまま首の意思なんだろうか？
Or...
それとも…
What're you filming?
何を撮ってるんだ？
Um, you know, I'm filming every
aspect of my daily life to leave to posterity.
いや… なんというか
甘い日常の断面を
一切合財 語り尽くして 後世に残そうかと。
Well, whatever you're doing, do it quietly. I can't sleep.
なんでもいいから 静かにしてくれ
眠れない
I'm sorry, Celty.
悪かったよ セルティ
Well, I'll end it here. We'll continue at a later time.
じゃあ このへんで
続きはまたいつか
Wow, that's perfect!
完ぺきじゃないですか！
Huh? What is? Dullahans are supposed to carry their heads with them.
どこが完ぺきなんだ
デュラハンは首を抱えているのが本来の姿なんだぞ？
It's fine if it doesn't have its head, right?
別になくたっていいんじゃないですか？ 首なんて
Of course it's not. You can say that
because you've never seen the real thing.
いいわけがない
実物を見ていないからそんなことを言うんだ
She was an incredibly beautiful woman.
世にも美しい女だったんだよ
I'm sure.
ですよね
Hm?
But I still think she looks better without her head.
でも やっぱり首はない方がいいなぁ
She's more charming that way.
その方がチャーミングですよ これで完ぺきです
It's perfect as it is.
Therefore, there's no need for you to worry.
だから おじいさんも悩むことはないんですよ
It's fine if you can't draw her head.
描けなくたっていいんです ずっとこのままで…
Even if you never can...
I'm still going to draw it.
だが 私は描く
I said it's fine as it is.
いいんですって これで！
You sure are weird.
変わった男だなぁ あんた
No, I'm not that weird.
いやぁ～ それほどでも
制作：LASTZZZ 安静の云 akira アキラ
You want to know about my seductive suaveness and heartbreaker lifestyle?
オレのラブラブゲッチューで
ハートブレイキンな日常を知りたいか？
Then take the channel of your heart and tune it in to me, the cool yet shy Kida Masaomi.
なら 君のハートのチャンネルを
漫游字幕组
http://popgo.net/bbs/
このシャイでクールな紀田正臣に合わせてくれ～！
Next time: False Advertising.
Don't miss out on this once-in-300-years chance!
３００年に一度のチャンスを見逃すな！